So is there a difference between
wanting to be happy and seeking freedom
from suffering? Well, yeah,
Well, yeah,
doesn't need to be.
If you understand that the greatest
happiness is being free from suffering,
then you could align both projects into
one. But um if you're using the uh the
But um if you're using the uh the
worldly measures of happiness
uh then they're usually taking you in a
different directions of um the direction
required for being free from suffering.
In other words, they'll take you to
direction of um acquiring possessions,
finding safety in things, connections,
family, sensuality, desires. basically
uh pacifying your mind providing it with
what it wants is what people regard as
happiness. But obviously if they start reflecting
But obviously if they start reflecting
on the whole problem on the whole lack
of satisfaction implicit in it the risk
the lack of safety implicit in in all
those things then they would realize
that it's really like a trap. It's not
really a happiness in the sense that
that's like truly safe and and truly
just um not not kind of subject to to
like circumstances
um others and so on.
For that uh yeah for that you need to
basically u make quite a bit of effort
to uncover and kind of realign and
change the values of where your views
are like what you think happiness is.
Um but fundamentally there is a common
thread though like people would be
engaging with sexuality, acquiring
possessions, forming connections um uh
everything else that people do they
would do it because fundamentally
not fulfilling those desires is
unpleasant. So then happiness is deeply rooted in
So then happiness is deeply rooted in
avoidance of discomfort. That's what's
perceived to be happiness. If I can
avoid the displeasure, I'll be happy.
I'll be contented.
Getting what you want is just basically
avoiding the displeasure of not having
it yet.
And uh and the same that same thread
remains even for somebody who practices
rightly. You recognize I'm pray to
suffering. I'm subject to suffering. The
ultimate happiness and peace is
basically when I'm when I would be
unable to suffer.
Um, so it's still rooted in the same
like desire to be free from suffering,
but then you realize, well, the first
type of desire just goes around and kind
of perpetuates the suffering through
engaging with things that are set up and
blamed for lack of happiness and so on.
But the second type of desire recognizes
that all of these things are futile.
They just like scratching the edge offer
temporary superficial relief while
underneath that making the the infection
worse. So then they say, "No, I'll
abstain from all these seeming instant
gratifications and satisfactions of my
discomfort and I'll stay with the
discomfort so I can hopefully see
through it and approot the real
problem." And see that type of desire can result
And see that type of desire can result
in completely uprooting the desire
because first and foremost, you're not
fueling it anymore through your behavior
and actions. And second, you are
actually looking through it, seeing
where the problem really is.
And the problem is in you craving
in regard to what you feel.
The problem is not in simply what you're
feeling currently.
So when there is craving removed in
regard to pleasure, in regard to pain,
in regard to neutral feeling, there is
no possibility of suffering to touch you
ever again.
>> And where is the feeling to be found?
>> Wherever it's felt.
which is where
>> which is where the domain of feeling is
saying where is the feeling implies kind
of a sense of space which comes on a
kind of perception and that's not where
feelings are felt.
So the question where is the feeling
colloquially speaking yes of course you
can say that and answer it but if you're
really looking where the feeling is
you're not you're not seeing it because
feeling can be felt not perceived.
So what where is my feeling? Well just
ask yourself overall in the broadest
sense how am I feeling right now? Is it
positive, negative or neutral? There is
no fourth option.
And you'll see and the more you practice
that the clearer that general nature of
feeling becomes that questioning through
that recollection.
But the more you expect to observe your
feeling the further away from your
feeling you're actually drifting
because that's where craving exists. It
doesn't exist on a level of this
molecular molecular m momentary sort of
second to second kind of oversightes
that you like split second and you
overlook something and craving came in.
No craving exists in that broadest
framework of your feeling that you
completely have no clue about because
you're looking for your feelings over
there over there. Sometimes you might
think about it in broad terms but never
to that sense. Hold on. What is the like
what am I factually feeling in the
broadest sense? Pleasure like right now
for the duration of this experience now
when I brought it up through my
recollection. What is the current
feeling that's enduring in the broadest
sense? Oh, this specifically I like this
specific things that it's like none of
those are feelings. Oh, I have these
sensations. It's like none of those are
feeling. Those are all perceptions.
Feeling is
do I feel okay? Do I feel not okay? Do I
feel neither okay nor not okay? That's
where you look for feelings and not too
much and not too little.
Like if you think again through asking
those questions, you're going to
crystallize it and see it in front of
you. No, it's always underneath you.
It's always behind you.
It's always the the the the weather you
are in.
you can't step outside of it.
>> And so if someone still has doubt about
this more general level of feeling that
you are now describing, can they ask do
I want this experience as a whole to
more or less continue the way it is or
am I sort of leaning towards wanting it
to become otherwise in
>> Yeah. anything that would make them
basically start feeling
on that level on that very general
general quite ambiguous in the beginning
non-defined level is it's almost like not even going
level is it's almost like not even going
to it's going to feel like oh but this
is I need to define it more and that's
that's the lack of the the mental
training when the mind is not trained
enough it cannot operate on those levels
they seem ambiguous they seem too subtle
because it's not used to staying with
them But factually take any person with
zero knowledge of anything and ask them
how do you feel right now? Just and the
answers that you can give me is
positive, negative or neutral. Those are
the three options. Don't proliferate
into psychology and start giving me the
concoctions of this and that. Just in
the broadest sense, would you say I'm
okay? I feel okay. In the broadest
sense, I don't feel okay
or I feel neither okay nor okay. and
then stay with that. When you find that
answer, let it endure. Don't try to,
okay, what do I ask next? No, no, no.
You're not supposed to ask anything.
If you reveal it, you don't have to ask
anything else then. You just have to
learn how to start feeling it on that
level because yes, you can have like see
because yes, you can have like see
somebody can be bothered by this
specific thing or that specific thing,
but overall their mood is okay. And if
you were to ask them, they would know
that. They cannot not know that.
And equally, somebody can have every
whim and desire catered to them,
every immediate kind of craving,
perception satisfied, but they're in a
bad mood.
Which means none of this will matter
because they're in a bad mood.
And that's the point to recognize, oh,
that mood, that weather is kind of what
gives the inclinations, the pressures,
and so on. So the more you're discerning
it, the closer to the roots of the
problem you get. That's where the
craving is. That's where the whole
leaning away from pain or leaning
towards pleasure happens. Not in front
of you in this, as I said, momentto-
moment observational
um experiences or something. No, it's on
the level of the framework. So if the
weather is good, I want more of it
implicitly at the back of my mind.
If the weather is bad, I want less of it
implicitly at the back of my mind. Even
if I don't think about it. But now if I
start paying attention to what's at the
back of my mind, I get to see then what
kind of attitudes I cultivate towards
it.
So the attitude is in relation to the
presently enduring feeling.
>> Yes. Presently enduring feeling at the
back of your mind.
>> And what needs to be purified is not the
feeling but the attitude.
>> Yeah. Basically what needs to be
purified is you your views regarding it.
Uh your deemphasis of those levels, you
looking past it, ignoring it and trying
to find things that are more palpable,
more measurable, more perceivable.
That's why sense restraint has to come
first to prevent you from just making
things worse in inadvertently.
Because the more you're engaging with
sense objects willingly through choice
on the basis of passion, aversion and so
on, the more your sense basis, the more
the the the background of your mind is
obscured.
The further away it is, the more
abstract it is when you think about it.
You don't see the concreteness of those
moods. You see them as things that come
and go secondarily to your point of
view, to your experience as a whole. But
it's other way around. You start looking
at those moods rightly, you'll see that
actually you and your experience as a
whole is within mood, not other way
around. >> And that is how you can see that you
>> And that is how you can see that you
have no say in the mood. Because in the
sense, >> that's how you eventually basically stop
>> that's how you eventually basically stop
assuming your sense of self outside of
your experience.
And that's the aim.
>> Yes,
exactly.